

■ nathanryanfrank@gmail.com | 🎓 nrfrank.github.io | 🖸 nrfrank | 🛅 nrfrank | 🗃 nathanfrank



#### About.

Skilled machine learning leader with experience in all aspects of the machine learning and software development life cycle. Former Astrophysicist turned data scientist and machine learning engineer with a proven history of delivering results into production across a wide variety of domains while leading projects with international, cross-functional teams.

# **Experience**

**Strong Analytics** 

Chicago, IL

DIRECTOR OF MACHINE LEARNING ENGINEERING

Apr. 2021 - Present

- Lead and mentor an international team of engineers supporting delivery across over a dozen Strong projects overseeing efforts in MLOps and DevOps, model optimization and deployment, ETL pipelines, streaming microservices, and full stack web development.
- Automated model training and evaluation pipeline (AWS EventBridge, Step Function, and Batch), **decreasing deployment lifecycle** from monthly to weekly and improving responsiveness of the client's automated content monitoring system.
- Served as project manager and technical lead for client building out a grocery product identification and recommendation service.
  - Implemented request volume monitoring and horizontally auto-scaling infrastructure, enabling >200 QPS system throughput.
  - Optimized and deployed feature extraction (DELG) and detection (YOLOv5) models to **Triton** services, **reducing inference time** ~ **50%**.
  - Oversaw development of web platform for dataset annotation and management, model analysis, and endpoint generation, enabling the rapid creation of dozens of custom, domain-specific customer endpoints.
- Collaborated to architect and build streaming user classification service. Trained and optimized model using sci-kit learn and ONNX and deployed to Triton service. Integrated model service within API processing Kafka events, utilizing Redis for caching.

SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST Aug. 2020 - Apr. 2021

- Deployed suite of forecasting models for health system records to **Databricks** and built jobs for dataset generation (**Spark**), model training and inference (**scikit-learn** and **PyTorch**), and API deployment (**MLflow**).
- Led analysis of student activity and course content data for a professional education platform, utilizing text embedding, graph network analysis, and sequential forecasting methods to enable automated course creation and content delivery.

## Stats Perform (formerly STATS, LLC)

Chicago, IL

Al Scientist [Tech Lead, ML Platform]

Jan. 2020 - Aug. 2020

- Architected and led development of an enterprise machine learning platform, integrating tools for model experimentation (MLflow), training (Docker and Batch), feature engineering (Athena and Tecton), and deployment (EKS), leading to a reduction in average model deployment time from months to days.
- Productized GNN-based model to predict minutes played of NBA players with RMSE lower than human domain experts.

#### Al Scientist [Tech Lead, STATS VQ]

Jan. 2019 - Jan. 2020

- Led international team of 13 data scientists and engineers in building a predictive player props API for sports books, generating \$500k of new business.
- Provided technical oversight of the VQ product: cloud data lake (AWS S3, Glue & Athena), Java Spark ETL pipeline, TensorFlow based model development framework, cloud infrastructure (AWS), human-in-the-loop interface and both internal and client-facing APIs.

Data Scientist Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2019

- **STATS Edge**: Collaboratively refactored legacy data science pipeline from Python jobs to **Apache Spark ETL** pipeline in a paired programming (XP) setting, reducing runtime and scaling volume 10x. **Optimized** and deployed existing models to Flask API, **reducing inference time by an order of magnitude**.
- NBA Live Win Probability: Achieved SOTA accuracy (88%) predicting end of game outcomes for NBA games given in-game context through the use of embedding techniques. Processed and released a curated dataset containing 352 features of over 8.7M NBA plays.

## Dept. of Physics & Astronomy, UNC - Chapel Hill

Chapel Hill, NC

RESEARCH & TEACHING ASSISTANT

Aug. 2011 - Jan. 2017

- Developed an analytic model of afterflow emission from structured, off-axis Gamma-ray Bursts (GRBs) with results comparable to 3D MHD simulations.
- Builder of **PROMPT-SSO** and contributor to the **Skynet Robotic Telescope Network**: a collection of fully automated telescopes, control software, image and data processing pipeline, and web interface.
- Head instructor for Introductory Astronomy Lab. Organizer and host of Morehead Observatory Guest Night, a weekly public astronomy presentation.

Education \_\_\_\_\_

### The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

PhD Candidate (ABD), Physics & Astronomy

Chapel Hill, NC

Jun. 2014 - Jan. 2017

- Advanced to candidacy by completing all coursework as well as qualifying and preliminary exams.
- Dissertation: Structured Energy Profiles in Gamma-ray Burst Afterglows: Analytic Calculation of Images and Light Curves for Direct Modeling

MS, Physics & Astronomy

Aug. 2011 - May 2014

• Thesis: Application of a Toy Model of Jet Structure to the Afterglow of GRB 080710

# University of California, Santa Cruz

Santa Cruz, CA

BS, Physics (Astrophysics), Honors

Sep. 2004 - Jun. 2009

• Thesis: Searching for Millisecond Pulsars in Gamma-ray Data Using the Fermi LAT

### Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

2018	Most Disruptive Entry (2nd Place Overall), Vista Consulting Group AI/ML Hackathon	Chicago, IL
2017	Most Creative Entry (4th Place Overall), Automated Insights/Amazon Alexa Hackathon	Durham, NC
2015	Graduate Research Fellowship, NC NASA Space Grant	Chapel Hill, NC
2014	Graduate Research Fellowship, NC NASA Space Grant	Chapel Hill, NC

# Presentations

Apr 2022 Basketball Analytics Summit, "How to Begin Your Journey: Hands on Basketball Analytics in Python"	webinar
Apr 2021 Basketball Analytics Summit, "Analytics in the Wild: Advice and Insights from Real World Applications"	webinar
May 2020 CSBA - Analytics Learning Academy, "Artificial Intelligence in Sports"	webinar
Apr. 2019 Basketball Analytics Summit, "Artificial Intelligence in Sports"	Durham, NC
Nov. 2018 <b>Promotable Data and Sports</b> , "Artificial Intelligence in Sports"	Chicago, IL
Sep. 2017 Painless/WISE Sports & Tech Event, Panel discussion on Sports and Technology.	Chicago, IL

FEBRUARY 2, 2023 NATHAN R. FRANK · CURRICULUM VITAE